<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://gsadovski.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://gsadovski.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-03-28T04:49:05+00:00</updated><id>https://gsadovski.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle></subtitle><entry><title type="html">Gravitational waves</title><link href="https://gsadovski.github.io/blog/2025/gwaves/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gravitational waves"/><published>2025-03-27T23:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-03-27T23:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gsadovski.github.io/blog/2025/gwaves</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gsadovski.github.io/blog/2025/gwaves/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>Gravitational waves (g-waves) are propagating modes of the gravitational field, and an old prediction from general relativity (GR). They were first proposed in 1916 by A. Einstein himself, and have a tensorial and massless nature. Additionally, g-waves can only be produced by energy-momentum distributions with non-vanishing 2nd order time derivative of their quadrupole (or higher) moments.</p> <p>G-waves in GR are analog of the electromagnetic waves (e-waves) in Maxwell’s theory of electromagnetism. And, just like light, carry important information about their source. They are irreplaceable when all other channels of radiation (electromagnetic, neutrinos, cosmic rays, <em>etc</em>.) are blocked. For instance, when two black holes coalesce (a BH-BH merger).</p> <p>This is why g-waves were such a big news a few years back. The first ever detection happened in 2015, when the interferometry observatories LIGO and Virgo simultaneously observed the same BH-BH merger, 1.3 billion light-years away from Earth <a class="citation" href="#ligo2016a">(LIGO and Virgo Collaborations, 2016)</a>. This event, named <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GW150914">GW150914</a>, was completely invisible to us otherwise (see Video 1). Thus, its detection represented the birth of a completely new era in astronomy, similar to the first use of the telescope to observe the night sky, done by Galileo Galilei in 1609.</p> <p>G-waves can also be used in addition to other channels, when they are unblocked. This is known as <em>multichannel</em> or <em>multi-messenger astronomy</em>, and has the potential to revolutionize astrophysics. For example, our understanding of coalescing neutron stars (NS-NS mergers). Such events emit much weaker signals, as they consist of much smaller masses. So, it took longer to detect. But, in 2017, it finally happened. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GW170817">GW170817</a> was the first (and, so far, the only) NS-NS merger observed via g-waves <a class="citation" href="#ligo2017a">(LIGO and Virgo Collaborations, 2017)</a>.</p> <p>Approximately 1.7s after GW170817, its electromagnetic counterpart arrived in the form of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma-ray_burst#">short gamma-ray burst</a>, detected by the Fermi and INTEGRAL space telescopes. Finally, approximately 11hs later, the optical part revealed itself as a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kilonova">kilonova</a>, ~140 million light-years away in the lenticular galaxy NGC4994, located at the Hydra constellation. The kilonova was observed by traditional telescopes all around Earth, and lasted a few weeks shinning across all the electromagnetic spectrum — from X-rays to visible light to infrared (check Video 2).</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Zt8Z_uzG71o?si=OrQwmyTVJ4xIIqEl" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1 w-100" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> <div class="caption"> Video 1: A computer simulation of the gravitational lensing around GW150914. </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/e7LcmWiclOs?si=cWPyfS4HuYkmFKV6" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1 w-100" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> <div class="caption"> Video 2: An animation timelapse of the events following GW170817 during the span of 9 days. </div> </div> </div> <p>GW150914 and GW170817 are two of the most impactful events in the 21st century physics. The <a href="https://breakthroughprize.org/Laureates/1/P4/Y2016">2016 Special Breakthrough Prize in Fundamental Physics</a>, the <a href="https://gruber.yale.edu/prize/2016-gruber-cosmology-prize">2016 Gruber Prize in Cosmology</a>, the <a href="https://vis.sciencemag.org/breakthrough2017/">2017 Breakthrough Of The Year</a>, and the <a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/2017/press-release/">2017 Nobel Prize in Physics</a> were all dedicated to them.</p> <h2 id="what-are-gravitational-waves">What are gravitational waves?</h2> <p>Just like one recognizes small ripples propagating across a lake as water waves (Figure 1), one could recognize small ripples rolling across the fabric of spacetime as g-waves. This is, of course, quite an idealized scenario, but which helps us understand and easily visualize wave phenomena.</p> <p>In reality, we know most waves are quite messy and difficult to precisely describe. To illustrate, it is enough to consider a windy day. The surface of the lake might become so choppy it might be hard to distinguish ripples from their surroundings (Figure 2). The lack of clear separation might force you to point to the whole lake as a single wavy mess. And to describe it mathematically, in a nice closed form, might be extremely hard, if not impossible.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/welldef-wave.webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/welldef-wave.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1 w-100" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Figure 1: Idealized wave. </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/illdef-wave.webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/illdef-wave.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1 w-100" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Figure 2: Messy wave environment. </div> </div> </div> <p>The same can happen to spacetime, <em>e.g.</em>, in the vicinity of a BH-BH merger. In fact, GW150914 produced so much energy in the form of g-waves, one would have to imagine a wind turbine so powerful, it would outshine the light production of all the stars in the entire observable universe. This was the level of chaos unleashed. Video 3 illustrate how choppy spacetime got in the vicinity of GW150914. Pay attention to the last 20 milliseconds. This is when the g-wave production peaked, and the power output outshone the observable universe 50 times over!</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YnCccVDpmrw?si=tRta7SNxGQbIOrI1" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1 w-100" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="" width="auto" height="auto"/> </figure> <div class="caption"> Video 3: Spacetime curvature around GW150914. </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> </div> </div> <p>G-waves can very easily produce a messy environment due to their natural non-linear behavior. They are dynamically described by Einstein’s field equations, which consist of 10 non-linear partial differential equations (nPDEs). In vacuum, they read $\mathrm{Ric} = 0$, and look deceptively simple. However, they imply g-waves are described by the curvature of spacetime, and also that g-waves produce and interact with the curvature of spacetime. This is known as <em>backreaction</em>, and has important net effects: g-waves can refract, reflect, redshift, backscatter, damp, <em>etc.</em>, all in vacuum.</p> <p>For comparison, e-waves are much more well-behaved. Dynamically, they are described by Maxwell’s equations which are linear PDEs. In some sense, they are still curvature, but linearity means that it does not interact with itself. Thus, to be messy, light really needs to interact with matter or with gravity. Only then it can refract, reflect, redshift, backscatter, damp, <em>etc</em>.</p> <p>In addition to the messiness of g-waves, a particularly energetic one can, in principle, undergo gravitational collapse. If focused on a small enough region, it can produce a black hole which destroys a portion of spacetime (geodesic incompleteness). We can hardly call this g-wave a ripple. A catastrophic megatsunami might be more fitting.</p> <p>It should be clear now that real g-wave phenomena are extremely complex. In fact, when serious astrophysicists want to realistically simulate g-wave production, they have no choice but to numerically solve the full set of nPDEs in a supercomputer. Unfortunately, I am not a serious astrophysicist. The g-wave solutions we’re going to discuss next are analytical: they can be written down in terms of elementary functions like $\sin(x)$, $\cos(x)$, $e^x$, <em>etc</em>. Mathematically, they are very nice. However, we should be very aware that “nice mathematics” just cannot cope with the richness of realistic g-waves. In other words, these analytical solutions don’t really exist in nature — they are too idealized. Nevertheless, they are useful as they carry qualitative features shared with real g-waves. So, I hope you can find them as interesting and illuminating as I do.</p> <h2 id="pp-wave-spacetimes">PP-wave spacetimes</h2> <p>Due to how the topic of g-waves is taught in undergrad courses all around the world, there is a misconception even among my colleagues, that we need first to linearize $ \mathrm{Ric} = 0 $. In other words, that we need to throw away the non-linearities of gravity, making it more similar to electromagnetism, in order to get analytical wavy solutions. This is, however, not true.</p> <p><em>Plane-fronted waves with parallel propagation</em> (pp-waves, for short) is a whole class of exact solutions of Einstein’s equations in vacuum, which describes fully non-linear g-waves. Admittedly, a generic solution in this class is not as immediate to intuitively understand and visualize. But, again, what’s really important is that no unnecessary sacrifices are made. These solutions carry all the non-linear behavior we expect from relativistic gravitational phenomena. Including chaos, caustics, shockwaves, singularity formation, <em>etc</em>.</p> <p>Consider spacetime to be a Lorentzian 4-manifold $\left(X,g\right)$, where $g(x)$ is known as <em>the metric tensor field</em>. The latter gives us a recipe on how to measure angles and sizes at each event $x \in X$ of spacetime. This is important. Field $g(x)$ is what comes out as solutions to Einstein’s field equations. In other words, it is the fundamental descriptor of gravity in GR.</p> <p>The family of pp-wave spacetimes consists of all $\left(X, g\right)$ which admits a covariantly constant null vector field $k$. This means $k$ needs to satisfy $g \left(k, k\right) = 0$ and $\nabla k = 0$. The physics savvy reader might be already suspicious that $k$ is the well-known wave vector — and you’re very right! But, at the same time, notice this definition required no physics. It consists of purely mathematical statements belonging to the realm of Lorentzian geometry. In particular, the null vector field condition is always locally guaranteed. What is really restrictive about this definition is the covariantly constant condition. This is what makes pp-wave spacetimes mathematically interesting: they contain Petrov type N regions.</p> <p>Pp-wave spacetimes locally admit the Brinkmann coordinate patch, defined as $\left(u, v, x, y\right) \; ; \; u \in \left(u_0,u_1\right),\; v,x,y \in \left(-\infty, +\infty\right) $, where $k= \partial_{v}$. On it, the metric tensor assumes the form</p> <div style="margin-top: -20px; margin-bottom: 0px;"> $$ g(x) = H \left(u,x,y\right) du^2 + 2 dudv + \overbrace{dx^2 + dy^2}^{\mathbb{E}^2} \;, $$ </div> <p>where $H \left(u, x, y\right)$ is $C^{\infty}$ (smooth) on the $xy$ Euclidean submanifold, $\mathbb{E}^2$, but otherwise arbitrary.</p> <p>Physics finally kicks in when we demand $g(x)$ to be a solution of $\mathrm{Ric} = 0$. One can show this is equivalent to demand $H$ to be harmonic on $\mathbb{E}^2$. Explicitly, $ \Delta H(u, x, y) = 0$, where $ \Delta \equiv \partial_{x}\partial_{x} + \partial_{y} \partial_{y}$ is the Laplacian differential operator on $\mathbb{E}^2$. No surprise, Einstein’s equations demand $H$ to oscillate (like a wave) in the $xy$ plane. In fact, surfaces of constant $(v_0,u_0)$ can be interpreted as propagating wavefronts!</p> <p>Clearly, $H$ encodes the particular details of each wavy solution. For instance, if $H = 0$ the metric is just flat Minkowski. If $H$ has compact support, the solution can be interpreted as g-wave packet (pulse). In fact, if $H(u,x,y) = \delta (u) H(x,y)$ we have <em>impulsive g-waves</em> (shockwaves). If $H$ is quadratic in $xy$, the wavefronts have plane geometry: solutions are non-linear plane g-waves. And so on, and so forth.</p> <h2 id="post-minkowskian-g-waves">Post-Minkowskian g-waves</h2> <p>Now that we cleared out some misconceptions, let’s address the more pedagogical approach — the one usually taught in undergrad courses. The end result is way easier to visualize, but to the expense of exactness. They’re only approximations of already idealized solutions.</p> <p>Let’s first establish the simplest solution to Einstein’s equations in vacuum: the already mentioned Minkowski spacetime. This is the globally flat manifold denoted by $\left(X,\eta\right)$, where</p> \[\eta \left(x\right) = -dt^2 + dx^2 + dy^2 + dz^2 \;,\] <p>and $t,x,y,z \in \left(-\infty, +\infty\right)$ is the globally defined Cartezian patch. Because Minkowski is everywhere flat, it is also destitute of any gravitational fields. One could say it is the <em>lowest energy</em>, most boring solution of $\mathrm{Ric} = 0$. Thus, it is the perfect background to study how ripples propagate.</p> <p>Second, we want to describe a scenario similar to Figure 1, where there is a clear separation between ripples and their surrounding background. In other words, a solution equivalent to “$\eta$ plus ripples”. Mathematically, we propose $g’ = f^{\ast} g \; ; \; g’ \equiv \eta + h$, where $f: \left(X,g’\right) \rightarrow \left(X,g\right)$ is a diffeomorphism.</p> <p>The equation $g’ = f^{\ast} g$ means $g$ is equivalent to $g’$. This is because Einstein’s field equations are covariant under transformation $f$. Saying it differently, $g$ and $g’$ represent the same physical solution: Minkowski with ripples. To be clear, $h(x)$ is a symmetric rank-2 tensor field representing these ripples. Mathematically, if $g$ is a solution, then $g’$ is a solution as well, which means $\mathrm{Ric} \left(g’, \partial g’, \partial^{2} g’\right) = 0$. Moreover, we also know $\eta$ is yet another solution — in fact, the globally constant most boring one, $\partial \eta = \partial^2 \eta = 0$ — which brings the final result to</p> \[\mathrm{Ric} \left(\eta, h, \partial h, \partial^2 h\right) = 0 \;. \label{eq:einstein-eq-for-h} \tag{1}\] <p>We clearly achieved separation since Einstein’s equations now became differential only for $h$. One could say we’re now dealing with a traditional $h$ field theory over a fixed Minkowski background. This is known as the <em>post-Minkowskian regime</em> of GR. The only “problem” is that \eqref{eq:einstein-eq-for-h} is still nonlinear, which means complicated dynamics and potentially messy solutions just like before. Our next step is to find a way to simplify this by discarding all the non-linearities, <em>a.k.a.</em>, let’s make gravity similar to the electromagnetism.</p> <h2 id="perturbation-theory">Perturbation theory</h2> <p>The messiness brought by non-linearities can manifest in the real world as caustics, shockwaves, phase transitions, turbulence, singularities, <em>etc</em>. Thus, it is nothing but reasonable to expect $h$ to be, at the very most, a $C^{\infty}$ field. In fact, \eqref{eq:einstein-eq-for-h} only demands it to be $C^2$ (twice differentiable). Figure 2, again, represents quite an extreme case — but not at all uncommon — in which smoothness is definitely absent, and $C^0$ (continuity) is questionable.</p> <p>One way to control these complexities is to demand $h$ to be $C^{\omega}$ (analytic<sup id="fnref:analytic"><a href="#fn:analytic" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>). This is quite a restrictive assumption, which is only satisfied by a very small fraction of all possible solutions to \eqref{eq:einstein-eq-for-h}. Analyticity forbids caustics, singularities, phase transitions, <em>etc.</em>, but also $h$ to be compactly supported on $X$. If a $C^{\omega}$ solution has compact support, then it is necessarily trivial (everywhere vanishing). This is because every $C^{\omega}$ solution is globally determined by its behavior in a local neighborhood of its domain — which is also a non-causal feature. If it vanishes somewhere, it has to vanish everywhere. Thus, every non-trivial $C^{\omega}$ solution is necessarily eternal and omnipresent (globally type N), and incapable of describing g-wave generation by localized sources.</p> <p>At times, analyticity might be a physical sacrifice worth paying for. Pedagogically, $C^\omega$ solutions are easier to understand and visualize. They are computationally simple to obtain. And, physically, some of them still share qualitative features with their more physical non-analytic counterparts. If $h$ is assumed $C^{\omega}$ on $X$, then it has an exact representation in terms of a Taylor series,</p> \[h (x) = \sum_{n=0}^{\infty} \frac{1}{n!}\nabla_{\dot{\gamma}(0)}^{(n)} h \mid_{\gamma (0)} \;, \label{eq:taylor-series} \tag{2}\] <p>where $\gamma: [0,1] \rightarrow X$ is a smooth curve connecting $\gamma (0) \equiv x_0 $ to $\gamma (1) \equiv x$. Again, the right-hand side of \eqref{eq:taylor-series} is a convergent power series locally defined in the neighborhood of $x_0$, but which determines $h(x)$ over the entire $X$.</p> <p>A less restrictive way to control the non-linearities is to assume the domain of $h$ admits an asymptotic scale, denoted by the set of fields $ \{ h^{(n)}(x) \} $. In this case, $h$ just needs to be $C^{0}$, and we technically keep most of its non-analytic behavior. However, there is a mathematical price to be paid. Equation \eqref{eq:taylor-series} is eroded into an equivalence to an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asymptotic_expansion">asymptotic expansion</a>,</p> \[h(x) \sim \sum_{n=0}^{\infty} h^{(n)}\;. \label{eq:asymptotic-series} \tag{3}\] <p>The right-hand side of \eqref{eq:asymptotic-series} is what mathematicians call a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Formal_power_series">formal series</a>. Contrasting \eqref{eq:taylor-series}, this infinite sum has no obligation to converge to a finite quantity, much less one equals to $h(x)$. Fortunately, \eqref{eq:asymptotic-series} is not pure mathematical wizardry, and we can give a rigorous meaning to $\sim$. For any finite truncation, the reminder</p> \[\mathcal{R}_N (x) \equiv h - \sum_{n=0}^N h^{(n)}\] <p>has to be strictly smaller than the leading order as $x$ approaches the future null infinity $\mathcal{I}^+$ of $\left(X,\eta\right)$. With this restriction, it is possible to define an equivalence class in which \eqref{eq:asymptotic-series} rigorously holds.</p> <p>Physicists like to call either of these techniques <em>perturbation theory</em>. The goal is to find a truncation of either \eqref{eq:taylor-series} or \eqref{eq:asymptotic-series}, depending on your assumptions, which approximates “well enough” the exact solution you’re trying to study. The higher the truncation order you need, the bigger is the piece you have to evaluate. The bigger the piece, the better the approximation is. However, these methods have very quickly diminishing returns.</p> <p>The leading order is always the 1st, which is also the linear limit. Beyond leading order truncations represent non-linear effects being carefully introduced as ever smaller corrections. At high orders, we pay a very large computational price for a very tiny improvement. Thus, most research is done at the leading order. Nonetheless, there are occasions you would want to consider 2nd order truncations. After all, they give us the first glimpse of how non-linear effects come into play.</p> <h2 id="linear-g-waves">Linear g-waves</h2> <p>The $N=0$ truncation is just a constant. Minkowski plus a constant is diffeomorphically Minkowski again. Thus, the $0$-th order truncation is too low to result in anything interesting. Substituting \eqref{eq:asymptotic-series}, truncated at $N=0$, into \eqref{eq:einstein-eq-for-h}, just trivially results in the statement that Minkowski is globally flat — again, something we already know.</p> <p>Now, as stated before, the 1st order is the leading order, which is also the linear limit. Substituting \eqref{eq:asymptotic-series}, truncated at $N=1$, into \eqref{eq:einstein-eq-for-h}, results in</p> \[\Box h^{(1)} = 0 \;, \label{eq:linear-g-wave} \tag{4}\] <p>where $\Box \equiv \partial \cdot \partial$ is the d’Alembertian differential operator on Minkowski spacetime, and the gauge fixing condition, $\partial \cdot \bar{h}^{(1)} = 0$, was used<sup id="fnref:trace-reversed"><a href="#fn:trace-reversed" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. Now, this is something new. In fact, this is what Einstein found in 1916! Apart from the fact $h^{(1)}$ is tensorial, \eqref{eq:linear-g-wave} is the same mathematical equation which governs the dynamical behavior of e-waves in vacuum! In other words, at leading order in the post-Minkowskian approximation, Einstein’s field equations forces $h$ to behave as traditional linear waves.</p> <p>For an arbitrary truncation, we generally end up with</p> \[\Box h^{(N)} = f^{(N)} \;,\] <p>where $f^{(N)}$ is a function depending non-linearly on $h^{(N-1)}$ and its derivatives. So, the beyond leading order behavior is clear. The $N$-th order non-linearities, contained in $f^{(N)}$, are constructed out of the $(N-1)$-th order solutions, and behave as sources for $h^{(N)}$. Again, we see that non-linearities introduce self-interactions. In particular, higher order g-waves are generated by lower order g-waves: gravity generating gravity.</p> <p>We have to mention that truncations will inevitably break the diffeomorphism symmetry (covariance) of Einstein’s equations. The good news is that the breakage is only partial. This detail is actually quite important for the physics of g-waves. At leading order, an Abelian gauge symmetry remains, given by the field transformation</p> \[h^{(1)} \mapsto {h'}^{(1)} = h^{(1)} + L_{\xi} \eta \;, \tag{5}\label{eq:gauge-symmetry}\] <p>where $L_{\xi}$ is the Lie derivative along the smooth vector field $\xi$. Condition $ \partial \cdot \bar{h}^{(1)} = 0 $, used to gauge fix this symmetry, simplifed the dynamical equations in \eqref{eq:linear-g-wave}. However, most gauge fixings are flawed, and this one is no exception. So much so, \eqref{eq:gauge-symmetry} is itself a symmetry of $ \partial \cdot \bar{h}^{(1)} = 0$, if $\Box \xi = 0$. In summary, there are still gauge redundancies in \eqref{eq:linear-g-wave} which we will need to address before we can speak of the actual physical degrees of freedom (DoF) g-waves represent.</p> <h2 id="the-linear-plane-wave">The linear plane wave</h2> <p>Ironically, the most straightforward solution to \eqref{eq:linear-g-wave} is an analytic solution known as the <em>monochromatic</em> <em>linear plane wave</em>,</p> \[h^{(1)} = \mathrm{Re} \left( A e^{i k \cdot \mathbb{x}}\right) \;,\] <p>where $\mathrm{Re} (z) \equiv \left(z+\bar{z}\right)/2$ is the real part of $z \in \mathbb{C}$; $A$ is a real symmetric rank-2 tensor field known as the <em>polarization tensor</em> ; $k$ is the wave vector; and, $\mathbb{x} \equiv x^{\mu}\partial_{\mu}$ is the Euler vector field. There is nothing too complicated here, in fact, the piece $\mathrm{Re} (e^{ik \cdot \mathbb{x}}) = \cos (k \cdot \mathbb{x})$ just gives how $h^{(1)}$ oscillates, and $A$ gives the directions in which these oscillations happen.</p> <p>Monochromatic (single color) implies $h^{(1)}$ has a well-defined constant frequency. Consequentially, $k$ is a globally constant field, immediately satisfying $\nabla k = 0$. Moreover, \eqref{eq:linear-g-wave} imposes $\eta \left(k,k\right) h^{(1)} = 0$ on this solution. If $h^{(1)}$ is to be non-trivial, then necessarily $\eta(k,k)=0$. Together, these conditions imply that this solution indeed represent massless modes travelling along null geodesics, to which $k$ is tangent to: GR predicts g-waves travelling exactly at the speed of light. It is apparent now that the “Minkowski plus ripples” spacetime, at leading order $\left(X, \eta + h^{(1)}\right)$, belongs to the bigger class of pp-wave spacetimes.</p> <p>The equation $k \cdot \left( \mathbb{x} - \mathbb{x}_0 \right) = 0$ defines an infinite family of parallel planes — each plane labelled by a particular value of the vector field $\mathbb{x}_0$. This equation also states that $k$ is normal to these planes: the planes can be interpreted as wavefronts. This is where the name <em>plane wave</em> comes from. Additionally, the gauge fixing condition imposes $h^{(1)}(k) = 0$. Consequentially, all oscillatory behavior is confined to the wavefronts, <em>i.e.</em>, $A$ doesn’t have a projection on the $k$-direction. This property cements g-waves as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transverse_wave">transverse waves</a>.</p> <p>As promised, $C^{\omega}$ solutions are way easier to understand and work with, but they’re also quite artificial. We can clearly see that linear plane waves are eternal (wavefronts extend indefinitely to the past and to the future) and have an unrealistically high degree of symmetry (wavefronts are planes). Nonetheless, when interacting with matter they can still reflect, refract, diffract, <em>etc.</em>, as any other wave can. So, a lot of real physics can be done with them.</p> <h2 id="polarization-modes">Polarization modes</h2> <p>A peculiar feature of transverse waves is known as <em>polarization</em>. It describes changes in the oscillation direction of $h^{(1)}$ as each wavefront arrives. Mathematically, polarization is captured by $A$. Physically, it represents the most elementary DoF of a g-wave: all the independent variables that satisfy the dynamical equations, but also survive all the gauge fixing constraints.</p> <p>We introduced the g-wave ripple as the symmetric rank-2 tensor. In four spacetime dimensions, this means 10 field variables. However, at leading order, we also introduced the gauge fixing condition, $\partial \cdot h^{(1)} = 0$. Implicitly, at least 4 of these variables are dependent, <em>i.e.</em>, they’re gauge redundancies (non-physical artifacts of a gauge symmetry).</p> <p>In preparation for this section, we did mention that our gauge fixing was not perfect. In other words, there are still gauge artifacts among these 6 field variables we’re left with. To get rid of all artifacts, we need to fully fix symmetry \eqref{eq:gauge-symmetry}. This is done by enhancing our previous gauge fixing. The so-called <em>transverse traceless synchronous</em> (TTS) <em>gauge</em> is defined by</p> \[\partial \cdot h^{(1)} = 0 \;, \tag{transverse}\] \[\tr \left(h^{(1)}\right) = 0 \;, \tag{traceless}\] \[h^{(1)} \left(\partial_{t}\right) = 0 \;, \tag{synchronous}\] <p>and represents a total of 8 independent constraints. In this gauge, it is very clear that $h^{(1)}$ have only 10-8=2 independent field variable, <em>i.e.</em>, 2 physical DoF. These are known as the 2 <em>polarization modes</em> allowed for g-waves.</p> <p>The TTS gauge constraints concomitantly imply that the gauge symmetries acting upon g-waves are such that scalar, vectorial and traceful tensorial modes are all pure gauge, <em>i.e.</em>, they cannot propagate. Thus, g-waves have no choice but to fundamentally be tensorial traceless. Tensorial means it acts “volumetrically”, like stress in a material body. Traceless means it preserves angles, but not necessarily sizes (as we will see). This is also why they’re only excited by higher multipole moments of matter. The monopole and dipole couple to pure gauge modes of the post-Minkowskian gravitational field!</p> <p>As we just mentioned, being traceless and tensorial leaves g-waves with only two independent ways of being different. These are the so-called $+$ and $\times$ polarization modes. To visualize these modes, consider $h^{(1)}$ propagating in the $\partial_z $-direction, namely, $k= \omega \partial_{t} + k_z \partial_{z}$. To satisfy $\eqref{eq:linear-g-wave}$, the null condition $\eta \left(k,k\right)=0$ needs to be respected. This means $\omega = k_z$. Now, to satisfy the TTS gauge, $A$ can only be given by 2 free parameters. In a very convenient frame, its matrix notation reads</p> \[\left[A \left(\partial_{\mu}, \partial_{\nu}\right)\right] = \begin{bmatrix} 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; A_{+} &amp; A_{\times} &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; A_{\times} &amp; -A_{+} &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \end{bmatrix} \;.\] <p>Quite clearly we can decompose this in a linear combination of the $+$ and $\times$ modes,</p> \[h^{(1)} = h^{(1)}_{+} + h^{(1)}_{\times} \;,\] <p>where</p> \[\left[ h^{(1)}_{+} \left(\partial_{\mu}, \partial_{\nu}\right)\right] \equiv A_{+}\begin{bmatrix} 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; -1 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \end{bmatrix} \mathrm{Re} \left[ e^{i \omega ( t-z )} \right] \;,\] <p>and</p> \[\left[ h^{(1)}_{\times} \left(\partial_{\mu}, \partial_{\nu}\right)\right] \equiv A_{\times}\begin{bmatrix} 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 1 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \\ 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 &amp; 0 \end{bmatrix} \mathrm{Re} \left[ e^{i \omega ( t-z )} \right] \;.\] <p>Notice the chosen frame is such that the modes only differ by a similarity transformation,</p> \[h_{\times}^{(1)} = \frac{A_{\times}}{A_{+}} \mathcal{R}^T \left(\frac{\pi}{4}\right) h_{+}^{(1)} \mathcal{R} \left(\frac{\pi}{4}\right) \;,\] <p>where $\mathcal{R}(\theta)$ is the rotation operator, along the $z$ axis, by an angle $\theta$. In simpler terms, if you look at a g-wave at a particular angle (frame), its modes look indistinguishable! However, keep in mind, this is not a frame-independent reality.</p> <p>Let’s physically interpret $h_{+}^{(1)}$. If $A_{+}\mathrm{Re} \left[e^{i \omega (t-z)}\right] &gt;0$, its polarization tensor implies that, as each wavefront passes, the $xx$ component of the “Minkowski plus ripple” metric scales up, while the $yy$ component scales down. If $A_{+}\left[e^{i \omega (t-z)}\right] &lt; 0$, then the opposite happens.</p> <p>We did say quite a while ago that metrics are of fundamental importance as they give us a recipe on how to measure sizes and angles in a space. The angles here are untouched because, as we’ve established, g-waves are traceless. Thus, the passage of $h_{+}^{(1)}$ fundamentally alters our notion of sizes in the $xx$ and $yy$ directions. Meanwhile, the passage of $h_{\times}^{(1)}$ does exactly the same, but rotated $\pi/4$ radian (45°) in the $xy$ plane (see Animation 1).</p> <p>A monochromatic plane g-wave is, in general, a linear combination of $h_{+}^{(1)}$ and $h_{\times}^{(1)}$ (see Animation 2). And, to obtain the most general linear g-wave, we have to sum over all possible monochromatic linear g-waves. Namely,</p> \[h^{(1)} = \mathcal{F} \left[ h_{+}^{(1)} + h_{\times}^{(1)}\right] \;,\] <p>where $\mathcal{F}$ is a Fourier transform from the space of frequencies. Keep in mind though, this only holds true at leading order.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://www.einstein-online.info/wp-content/uploads/Gravitationswellen_Gravitationswelle_kreisfoermig_%C2%A9_Daniela_Leitner_Markus_Poessel_Einstein-Online-480.webp 480w,https://www.einstein-online.info/wp-content/uploads/Gravitationswellen_Gravitationswelle_kreisfoermig_%C2%A9_Daniela_Leitner_Markus_Poessel_Einstein-Online-800.webp 800w,https://www.einstein-online.info/wp-content/uploads/Gravitationswellen_Gravitationswelle_kreisfoermig_%C2%A9_Daniela_Leitner_Markus_Poessel_Einstein-Online-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="https://www.einstein-online.info/wp-content/uploads/Gravitationswellen_Gravitationswelle_kreisfoermig_%C2%A9_Daniela_Leitner_Markus_Poessel_Einstein-Online.gif" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Animation 1: The $h_{+}^{(1)}$ mode travelling through a cylindrical grid. To visualize $h_{\times}^{(1)}$, rotate the oscillations by 45°.</figcaption> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://www.einstein-online.info/wp-content/uploads/Gravitationswellen_Gravitationswelle_elliptisch_%C2%A9_Daniela_Leitner_Markus_Poessel_Einstein-Online-480.webp 480w,https://www.einstein-online.info/wp-content/uploads/Gravitationswellen_Gravitationswelle_elliptisch_%C2%A9_Daniela_Leitner_Markus_Poessel_Einstein-Online-800.webp 800w,https://www.einstein-online.info/wp-content/uploads/Gravitationswellen_Gravitationswelle_elliptisch_%C2%A9_Daniela_Leitner_Markus_Poessel_Einstein-Online-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="https://www.einstein-online.info/wp-content/uploads/Gravitationswellen_Gravitationswelle_elliptisch_%C2%A9_Daniela_Leitner_Markus_Poessel_Einstein-Online.gif" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Animation 2: A linear combination of $h_{+}^{(1)}$ and $h_{\times}^{(1)}$, such that $A_{+}/A_{\times} = 1$.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="detectors-designs">Detectors’ designs</h2> <p>Finally, to finish our discussion, we point out why g-waves observatories like LIGO and Virgo are made of 2 long arms separated by the most perfect 90° angle — this is also a great excuse for me to put here some very cool science-based landscape photos! Please, check Photos 1–3.</p> <p>To understand this unique design, we have to understand how we perceive an incoming g-wave. First, it’s very rare for a g-wave to have exactly the same amplitudes for both $+$ and $\times$ modes. It’s too much of a numerical coincidence, especially considering the chaotic environment they originate from. Additionally, the angle at which a g-wave hit us plays a significant role.</p> <p>If the source is a compact binary system, and its plane of orbit is parallel to the detector’s plane, <em>a.k.a.</em>, the g-wave hits us head on, then, due to the axial symmetry, it is impossible for us to distinguish between the modes. This is a direct consequence of that similarity transformation. In such cases, we perceive the incoming g-wave as almost purely polarized: either $+$ or $\times$ mode (which is Animation 1). If the planes are not parallel to each other, then we lose axial symmetry, and we can detect a mixture of $+$ and $\times$ modes to various degrees. Our sensibility to distinguish the modes is maximum when the planes are perpendicular to each other, <em>a.k.a.</em>, the g-wave hits us edge on (which is qualitatively Animation 2).</p> <p>In the best case scenario, which is a head on hit, we can clearly see that the detectors’ design maximizes the stretching/compressing effect on the arms. The 90° separation was carefully chosen to maximize the detectors’ sensitivity for these arrivals! On the other hand, this design choice compromises our ability to distinguish between the polarization modes. It is very obvious that the focus was to detect the first g-waves, not to study their nature in details.</p> <p>Something similar can be said about each arm’s length. The stretching/compression in Animations 1–2 are highly exaggerated for visualization purposes. In practice, these arrive at Earth as extremely tiny perturbations (smaller than the typical width of atomic nuclei!). We would need an extremely long pair of arms to have any significant absolute displacement. Currently, LIGO and Virgo operate at the very technological limit of Earth-based detectors, around 3 to 4 kilometers, respectively.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://www.ligo.caltech.edu/system/avm_image_sqls/binaries/52/page/HiResHanford_5.jpg?1465343234" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="https://www.ligo.caltech.edu/system/avm_image_sqls/binaries/52/page/HiResHanford_5.jpg?1465343234" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Photo 1: LIGO Hanford.</figcaption> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://www.ligo.caltech.edu/system/avm_image_sqls/binaries/30/page/ligo-livingston-aerial-02.jpg?1447107179" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="https://www.ligo.caltech.edu/system/avm_image_sqls/binaries/30/page/ligo-livingston-aerial-02.jpg?1447107179" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Photo 2: LIGO Livingston.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="row"> <div class="col"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://www.ligo.caltech.edu/system/avm_image_sqls/binaries/81/page/2015_11_06_VirgoAerialView_ToUpload_2_.jpg?1506480873" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="https://www.ligo.caltech.edu/system/avm_image_sqls/binaries/81/page/2015_11_06_VirgoAerialView_ToUpload_2_.jpg?1506480873" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Photo 3: Virgo.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <p>The next generation of detectors, which is currently being designed, is going to be space-based. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laser_Interferometer_Space_Antenna">LISA</a> (see Figures 3–4) is projected to have arms 2.5 million km long! You read that right, 2.5 million kilometer! Also, you can immediately see its configured quite differently. The arms close in an equilateral triangular shape. LISA is not biased towards head on arrivals. And, due to the $\pi/3$ rad (60°) separation between the arms, it breaks the similarity transformation which degenerates the $+$ and $\times$ modes. In summary, LISA can detect g-waves coming from all directions (full sky coverage), and it can also distinguish between polarization modes in head on arrivals.</p> <p>Next-gen detectors represent an increase between $10^2$ to $10^3$ times of our current sensibility, allowing us to observe the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gravitational_wave_background">gravitational wave background</a> (GWB). This is made of low-frequency g-waves which permeates the entire universe, analogous to the electromagnetic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmic_microwave_background">cosmic microwave background</a> (CMB). The GWB has many (possible) origins, supermassive BH-BH mergers, primordial cosmological phase transitions such as the <em>inflationary re-heating</em>, the <em>electroweak phase transition</em>, <em>etc</em>. Additionally, it has contributions from stellar mass BH-BH mergers, <em>supernovae</em>, <em>cosmic strings</em>, <em>etc.</em> Super exciting stuff.</p> <div class="row"> <div class="col"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://lisa.nasa.gov/archive2011/images/LISA_Constellation2_500px-480.webp 480w,https://lisa.nasa.gov/archive2011/images/LISA_Constellation2_500px-800.webp 800w,https://lisa.nasa.gov/archive2011/images/LISA_Constellation2_500px-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="https://lisa.nasa.gov/archive2011/images/LISA_Constellation2_500px.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 3: Artist's impression of LISA.</figcaption> </figure> </div> <div class="col"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/ad/LISA_motion-480.webp 480w,https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/ad/LISA_motion-800.webp 800w,https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/ad/LISA_motion-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/a/ad/LISA_motion.gif" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> <figcaption class="caption">Figure 4: LISA following Earth's orbit around the Sun.</figcaption> </figure> </div> </div> <h2 id="references">References</h2> <div class="publications"> <h2 class="bibliography">2017</h2> <ol class="bibliography"><li><div class="row"> <div class="col col-sm-2 abbr"> <abbr class="badge rounded w-100">AJL</abbr> </div> <div id="ligo2017a" class="col-sm-8"> <div class="title">Multi-messenger observations of a binary neutron star merger</div> <div class="author"> LIGO and Virgo Collaborations <i class="fa-solid fa-circle-info ml-1" data-toggle="popover" data-placement="top" data-html="true" data-content="First ever multi-messenger detection of gravitational waves."> </i> </div> <div class="periodical"> <em>The Astrophysical Journal Letters</em>, Oct 2017 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> <a class="abstract btn btn-sm z-depth-0" role="button">Abs</a> <a href="https://doi.org/10.3847/2041-8213/aa91c9" class="btn btn-sm z-depth-0" role="button">DOI</a> </div> <div class="abstract hidden"> <p> On 2017 August 17 a binary neutron star coalescence candidate (later designated GW170817) with merger time 12:41:04 UTC was observed through gravitational waves by the Advanced LIGO and Advanced Virgo detectors. The Fermi Gamma-ray Burst Monitor independently detected a gamma-ray burst (GRB 170817A) with a time delay of  1.7s with respect to the merger time. From the gravitational-wave signal, the source was initially localized to a sky region of 31 deg² at a luminosity distance of 40^+8_-8 Mpc and with component masses consistent with neutron stars. The component masses were later measured to be in the range 0.86 to 2.26 M⊙. An extensive observing campaign was launched across the electromagnetic spectrum leading to the discovery of a bright optical transient (SSS17a, now with the IAU identification of AT 2017gfo) in NGC 4993 (at  40 Mpc) less than 11 hours after the merger by the One-Meter, Two Hemisphere (1M2H) team using the 1 m Swope Telescope. The optical transient was independently detected by multiple teams within an hour. Subsequent observations targeted the object and its environment. Early ultraviolet observations revealed a blue transient that faded within 48 hours. Optical and infrared observations showed a redward evolution over  10 days. Following early non-detections, X-ray and radio emission were discovered at the transient’s position  9 and  16 days, respectively, after the merger. Both the X-ray and radio emission likely arise from a physical process that is distinct from the one that generates the UV/optical/near-infrared emission. No ultra-high-energy gamma-rays and no neutrino candidates consistent with the source were found in follow-up searches. These observations support the hypothesis that GW170817 was produced by the merger of two neutron stars in NGC 4993 followed by a short gamma-ray burst (GRB 170817A) and a kilonova/macronova powered by the radioactive decay of r-process nuclei synthesized in the ejecta.</p> </div> </div> </div> </li></ol> <h2 class="bibliography">2016</h2> <ol class="bibliography"><li><div class="row"> <div class="col col-sm-2 abbr"> <abbr class="badge rounded w-100">PRL</abbr> </div> <div id="ligo2016a" class="col-sm-8"> <div class="title">Observation of gravitational waves from a binary black hole merger</div> <div class="author"> LIGO and Virgo Collaborations <i class="fa-solid fa-circle-info ml-1" data-toggle="popover" data-placement="top" data-html="true" data-content="First ever detection of gravitational waves."> </i> </div> <div class="periodical"> <em>Physical Review Letters</em>, Feb 2016 </div> <div class="periodical"> </div> <div class="links"> <a class="abstract btn btn-sm z-depth-0" role="button">Abs</a> <a href="https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.116.061102" class="btn btn-sm z-depth-0" role="button">DOI</a> </div> <div class="abstract hidden"> <p>On September 14, 2015 at 09:50:45 UTC the two detectors of the Laser Interferometer Gravitational-Wave Observatory simultaneously observed a transient gravitational-wave signal. The signal sweeps upwards in frequency from 35 to 250 Hz with a peak gravitational-wave strain of 1.0×10−21. It matches the waveform predicted by general relativity for the inspiral and merger of a pair of black holes and the ringdown of the resulting single black hole. The signal was observed with a matched-filter signal-to-noise ratio of 24 and a false alarm rate estimated to be less than 1 event per 203 000 years, equivalent to a significance greater than 5.1σ. The source lies at a luminosity distance of 410+160−180 Mpc corresponding to a redshift z=0.09+0.03−0.04. In the source frame, the initial black hole masses are 36+5−4M⊙ and 29+4−4M⊙, and the final black hole mass is 62+4−4M⊙, with 3.0+0.5−0.5M⊙c2 radiated in gravitational waves. All uncertainties define 90% credible intervals. These observations demonstrate the existence of binary stellar-mass black hole systems. This is the first direct detection of gravitational waves and the first observation of a binary black hole merger.</p> </div> </div> </div> </li></ol> </div> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:analytic"> <p>Not to be confused with analytical. Every analytic function is analytical, but the other way around is false. <a href="#fnref:analytic" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:trace-reversed"> <p>This is the linearized harmonic gauge. In particular, $ \bar{h}^{(1)} \equiv h^{(1)} - \frac{1}{2} \eta \tr \left(h^{(1)}\right) $ is the <em>trace-reversed</em> representation of $h^{(1)}$. The name is justified because $\tr(\bar{h}^{(1)}) = -\tr\left(h^{(1)}\right)$. This is the same relationship between the Einstein tensor and the Ricci tensor in four spacetime dimensions. Namely, $\mathrm{Ein} = \mathrm{Ric}- \frac{1}{2}g \tr \left( \mathrm{Ric} \right)$. <a href="#fnref:trace-reversed" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name>Guilherme Sadovski</name></author><category term="physics"/><category term="gr-qc"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Milestone of the 21st century physics.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How predictive is General Relativity?</title><link href="https://gsadovski.github.io/blog/2025/cauchy-problem/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How predictive is General Relativity?"/><published>2025-02-05T23:37:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-05T23:37:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gsadovski.github.io/blog/2025/cauchy-problem</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gsadovski.github.io/blog/2025/cauchy-problem/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>Einstein’s equations in vacuum, given by $R_{\mu \nu} = 0$, consist of ten coupled non-linear generic partial differential equations (PDEs) for the Lorentzian 4-metric tensor field, $g_{\mu \nu}(x)$. Given the complexity of these dynamical equations, it is not immediately clear that General Relativity (GR) is a deterministic theory.</p> <p>Determinism is an important feature of physical theories. It implies that the whole past and future (the history) of a system can be evaluated, with infinite precision, from a minimal set of data. This makes deterministic theories extremely predictive, and thus appealing to the scientific framework.</p> <p>Mathematically, determinism can be captured by a system of equations whose solutions exist, and can be uniquely determined. Usually, the system is differential with respect to some affine parameter (time), and the minimal set of data is the Cauchy (initial) data. Systems like these are said to be a <em>well-posed Cauchy problem</em>.</p> <p>Examples in Physics are plenty: Newton’s 2nd Law, Newton’s Law of Gravitation, Maxwell’s equations, Schrödinger’s equation in the absence of measurements (collapses of the wave function), <em>etc</em>. Granted, these examples have much simpler dynamics than GR. Newton’s 2nd law and Schrödinger’s are ordinary differential equations. Newton’s Law of Gravitation and Maxwell’s are PDEs, but they are linear. Nonetheless, they reveal that what gives GR so much physical richness, is also what cripples its mathematical understanding, and possibly its predictability.</p> <p>A detailed study of GR’s dynamics needs to address the proof of existence and uniqueness of its solutions. As mentioned, a natural step is to attempt to formulate a well-posed Cauchy problem for Einstein’s equations. However, this has proven to be difficult to do.</p> <p>An important tool in this endeavor is the use of the harmonic gauge condition. In this gauge, Einstein’s equations assume the form of quasi-linear hyperbolic PDEs (wave-like equations). Choquet-Bruhat theorem then guarantees, at least, the <em>local</em> existence and uniqueness of solutions. In other words, GR is locally a well-posed Cauchy problem.</p> <p>The Arnowitt-Deser-Misner (ADM) formalism plays a major role in clarifying Choquet-Bruhat’s results. But it also implies a particular choice of global spacetime foliation. This is a more restricted framework, applicable to only a subspace of solutions.</p> <p>Finally, the <em>global</em> proof of existence and uniqueness is still an open problem in the mathematical-physics of GR. In fact, the theorems of existence of spacetime singularities, and the possible existence of Cauchy horizons indicate that a global proof might not exist. In other words, GR might not be a globally well-posed Cauchy problem.</p> <p>The Weak and Strong Cosmic Censorship Conjectures (CCCs) were formulated in an attempt to mitigate this situation. Nevertheless, recent and old results are pilling up against their validity. One is then left wondering how predictive GR really is.</p> <h2 id="the-harmonic-gauge">The harmonic gauge</h2> <p>GR has dynamics invariant under the group of diffeomorphisms among Lorentzian 4-manifolds. This means that its physical solutions are equivalence classes under these maps. Each class, or each physical solution, has many (actually, infinite) equivalent representatives. This enormous redundancy implies that Einstein’s equations are plagued with <em>gauge artifacts</em>, making them more complex than actually necessary to describe the physics of the gravitational field.</p> <p>Gauge fixing these redundancies give us a way to simplify Einstein’s equations without sacrificing its physical content. A cleaver choice is the so-called harmonic gauge fixing conditions, defined by 4 constraint equations,</p> \[\Box x^{\mu} = 0 \;,\] <p>where $\Box \equiv g^{\mu \nu} \nabla_{\mu} \nabla_{\nu}$ is the d’Alembertian differential operator.</p> <p>Applying the harmonic gauge conditions to Einstein’s equations in vacuum shapes them into the form</p> \[\tilde{\Box} g_{\mu \nu} = N_{\mu \nu} \left( g, \partial g\right) \;,\] <p>where $\tilde{\Box} \equiv g^{\mu\nu}\partial_{\mu}\partial_{\nu}$, and $N_{\mu \nu}$ is a smooth non-linear function up to the 1st derivative of $g_{\mu \nu}$. These are wave-like equations, mathematically classified as a set of 2nd order quasi-linear hyperbolic PDEs.</p> <p>Luckily, the branch of Analysis dealing with quasi-linear hyperbolic PDEs is more developed than the one of fully non-linear generic PDEs. For instance, if $N_{\mu \nu}$ were to be analytic, then the local existence and uniqueness would automatically follow due to the so-called Cauchy-Kowalevski theorem. Unluckily, $N_{\mu \nu}$ is smooth but non-analytical in most physical situations.</p> <p>In 1952, mathematical-physicist Yvonne Choquet-Bruhat managed to relax the analyticity condition via the use of Sobolev spaces (see <a href="https://inspirehep.net/literature/1322081">a review</a> by Yvonne herself). Her theorem was fully applicable to Einstein’s equation in the harmonic gauge, and thus guaranteed the local well-posedness of its Cauchy problem. In other words, Yvonne proved that GR has a deterministic evolution in a small enough neighborhood of its solution space.</p> <h2 id="the-adm-formalism">The ADM formalism</h2> <p>Let’s consider $\left(X, g_{\mu \nu}\right)$ a Lorentzian 4-manifold. If foliatable, there exists a diffeomorphism map $f: X \mapsto \mathbb{R}\times\Sigma$. This allows to define in $X$ a 1-parameter family of spacelike 3-manifolds, $\Sigma_{\lambda} \equiv {f}^{-1} \left(\left\{\lambda \right\} \times \Sigma \right) \; ; \; \lambda \in \mathbb{R}$, which are called the “leaves” in this foliation, check Figure 1.</p> <div align="center"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/svg/foliation.webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/svg/foliation.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Figure 1: Foliability of $X$. </div> </div> <p>Each leaf $\Sigma_{\lambda}$ has an induced 3-metric, $h_{ij} \left(\lambda\right)$, and an extrinsic curvature, $K_{ij} \left(\lambda\right)$. Furthermore, there also exists a globally well-defined, smooth, timelike vector field, $\partial_{\lambda}$, that generates a flow of time.</p> <p>Foliability implies something very mundane for all of us: that space and time are separable, almost orthogonal entities. We measure space with a ruler, time with a clock. Not ever a situation arose in which we needed both a rule and a clock to measure space, or a ruler and a clock to measure time. And, to be frank, this is always true as long as we are measuring a small enough neighborhood of spacetime (most of us never even left Earth anyway).</p> <p>In GR, however, foliability cannot always be guaranteed over the entire spacetime manifold (globally). Mind, this is a feature, not a bug, of GR’s full invariance under diffeomorphisms. Behind the scenes, the foliability condition actually selects solutions with partially broken invariance. A residual symmetry still exists on the leaves, but the breakage is just enough to allow a global notion of time, time evolution, initial data, <em>etc</em>. All welcomed ingredients for a well-posed Cauchy problem.</p> <p>The ADM formalism uses the foliability condition to split Einstein’s equations apart. Mind, there are many (infinite) ways to split Einstein’s equations apart, but the ADM one is remarkable because, by projecting Einstein’s equations onto the leaves, ADM precisely separates them in constraint <em>versus</em> dynamical equations. Concurrently, it establishes the trio $\left( \Sigma_{\lambda}, h_{ij}, K_{ij}\right)$ as their Cauchy data.</p> <h3 id="the-constraint-equations">The constraint equations</h3> <p>Not every Cauchy data $\left(\Sigma_{\lambda}, h_{ij}, K_{ij}\right)$ is compatible with a foliation of $\left(X, g_{\mu \nu}\right)$. The constraint equations exist to ensure this compatibility. Yvonne deduced these equations from energy estimates and properties of Sobolev spaces. But, using the ADM formalism, they naturally pop up as follows.</p> <p>Let $\pi_{ij} \equiv 4 \pi \sqrt{h} \left( K_{ij} - h_{ij} K \right) \; ; \; K \equiv h^{ij}K_{ij} $ be the conjugated momenta of $h_{ij}$. Einstein’s equation, $R_{00} = 0$, when projected onto the leaves, $\Sigma_{\lambda}$, results in the now famous Hamiltonian constraint,</p> \[H = 0 \;,\] <p>where $H \equiv - \sqrt{h} \left[ R^h + h^{-1} \left( \pi^{2} - \pi_{ij}\pi^{ij} \right) \right] \; ; \; \pi \equiv h^{ij}\pi_{ij}$, and $R^h$ is the curvature scalar of $h_{ij}$. On the other hand, when $R_{0i} = 0$ is projected onto $\Sigma_{\lambda}$, the result is the momentum constraint equations</p> \[P^i = 0 \;,\] <p>where $P^i \equiv -2 \nabla_j \pi^{ij}$.</p> <p>Together, the Hamiltonian and momentum constraints form a system of 4 PDEs that every Cauchy data for Einstein’s equations have to obey.</p> <p>Here, we cannot avoid but mention that, in quantum gravity, these are the constraint equations that lead to the famous Wheeler-DeWitt equations,</p> \[\begin{aligned} \hat{H} \lvert \Psi \rangle &amp;= 0 \;, \\ \hat{P}^i \lvert \Psi \rangle &amp;= 0 \;, \end{aligned}\] <p>for the quantum state $\lvert \Psi \rangle$ of the Universe. As well as to the problem of time, Ashtekar variables (a complex self-dual formulation of GR), and the loop representation of Carlo Rovelli and Lee Smolin, finally giving birth to Loop Quantum Gravity.</p> <h3 id="the-dynamical-ones">The dynamical ones</h3> <p>We discussed how Yvonne evolved her constrained set of Cauchy data via Einstein’s equations in the harmonic gauge. It turns out that the ADM formalism produces an even simpler description.</p> <p>First, let us establish that the flow of time happens in the direction of the vector field $\partial_{\lambda} = \alpha \hat{n} + \vec{\beta}$, where $\alpha$ is the so-called lapse function, $\hat{n}$ is the unit vector normal to $\Sigma_{\lambda}$, and $\vec{\beta}$ the displacement vector implicitly given by the orthogonality condition $\hat{n} \cdot \vec{\beta} = 0$, see Figure 2.</p> <p>The dynamical evolution of $h_{ij}$ can be obtained from the very definition of the extrinsic curvature. Explicitly, $K_{ij} \equiv - L_{\alpha \hat{n}} h_{ij} / 2$, where $L_{\alpha \hat{n}}$ is the Lie derivative along $\alpha\hat{n}$. Solving for $L_{\partial_{\lambda}} h_{ij}$, one arrives at</p> \[\partial_{\lambda} h_{ij} = - 2 K_{ij} + L_{\vec{\beta}} h_{ij} \;.\] <p>This is a set of 10 quasi-linear 1st order PDEs, which give how the intrinsic local 3-geometry changes as we pass from one leaf, let’s say $\Sigma_{\lambda}$, to another infinitesimally close to it, let’s say $\Sigma_{\lambda + d\lambda}$.</p> <p>On the other hand, the dynamical evolution for $K_{ij}$ is given by the projection of Einstein’s equations, $R_{ij} = 0$, onto the leaves. Explicitly,</p> \[\partial_{\lambda} K_{ij} = \alpha \left[ R_{ij}^h + K_{ij} K - 2 K_{ik} K_j^k \right] \;,\] <p>where $R_{ij}^h$ is the Ricci tensor of $h_{ij}$. This is another set of 10 quasi-linear 1st order PDEs, which give how the local curvature, due to how the leaves “sit inside $X$”, changes within the infinitesimal time interval that separates $\Sigma_{\lambda}$ and $\Sigma_{\lambda + d\lambda}$.</p> <p>Now, it is supposed to be clear that we can exchange Einstein’s equations in the harmonic gauge, used by Yvonne and given by 10 2nd order PDEs, with the 20 1st order PDEs in the ADM formulation. Surely, we now have double the equations to solve, but they are also way simpler. This is in full analogy with the passage from the Lagrangian to the Hamiltonian formulation of Classical Mechanics. Particularly how $n$ Euler-Lagrange equations becomes $2n$ Hamilton’s equations. In fact, one way to interpret the ADM formalism is as a Hamiltonian description of GR.</p> <p>We stress that if GR is indeed fully deterministic, these dynamical equations can be used to evolve the Cauchy data $\left(\Sigma_{\lambda}, h_{ij}, K_{ij}\right)$ to ANY other leaf in the foliation, see Figure 3. This would be equivalent to know the entire plot of a movie from just a screenshot (unfortunately, not a rare occurrence these days). However, here the movie is the entire history of the Universe. This is what theoretical physicists and mathematicians mean when they speak of “a well-posed Cauchy problem for GR”.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/svg/timeflow.webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/svg/timeflow.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Figure 2: Flow of time. </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/svg/evolution.webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/svg/evolution.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Figure 3: Evolution of Cauchy data. </div> </div> </div> <h2 id="global-well-posedness">Global well-posedness</h2> <p>Two milestones towards the global proof of existence of solutions are: i) the <a href="https://inspirehep.net/literature/370148">1993 Christodoulou-Klainerman</a> theorem and; ii) the <a href="https://inspirehep.net/literature/614941">2003 Andersson-Moncrief</a> theorem.</p> <p>Result i) establishes the stability of Minkowski spacetime under small Cauchy data. In other words, the Minkowski solution exists for arbitrarily long periods of time and, solutions in its neighborhood tend to settle back towards it. This can also be interpreted as a theorem of non-existence of singularities in the space of solutions around Minkowski’s.</p> <p>Result ii) is similar in spirit and technique to i). It establishes the future stability of <em>hyperbolic cone spacetimes</em>, also for small enough Cauchy data. These are compactified variants of the familiar $\kappa = -1$ FLRW cosmological solutions, admitting foliations of constant mean curvature, <em>i.e.</em>, $\left\{\Sigma_{\lambda} \; ; \; K = \text{const.}\right\}$. The interpretation is analogous to the Minkowski’s case.</p> <p>As one can see, though important, the above theorems cover only very localized areas in the space of all solutions. In fact, to this day, we still lack a theorem that ensures existence of arbitrary solutions to Einstein’s equations. Thus, we can already conclude that the global well-posedness represents a major open problem in the mathematical-physics of GR. For completeness, let’s now address the global uniqueness.</p> <p>First, consider a differentiable timelike curve, $\gamma(\lambda) \; ; \; g \left(\gamma,\gamma\right) &lt; 0$, which extends indefinitely to the past and to the future (also called <em>inextensible</em>). A Cauchy surface $S$ is a subset of $X$ punctured only once by every inextensible differentiable timelike curve in $X$. This has already being qualitatively depicted in Figure 3 for a single curve. The single point of intersection captures, in essence, the uniqueness of Cauchy data in each leaf.</p> <p>Going back to the Choquet-Bruhat theorem, the local proof of uniqueness is in one-to-one correspondence with the existence of a Cauchy surface within the infinitesimal time interval $d \lambda$. In fact, one can always find a convenient local foliation in which every leaf is a Cauchy surface, also called a Cauchy foliation. Then, it is natural to expect that Yvonne’s theorem remains valid in a larger piece of spacetime as long as it admits a Cauchy foliation, like in Figure 3.</p> <p>In 1969, Yvonne, now collaborating with Robert Geroch, developed the concept of a <em>maximal globally hyperbolic developed</em> (MGHD), and proved its uniqueness up to diffeomorphisms. This is the largest possible piece of spacetime that admits a Cauchy foliation. And, thus, for which Einstein’s equations imply a deterministic evolution. In particular, the <a href="https://inspirehep.net/literature/59617">Choquet-Bruhat-Geroch result</a> represents a global uniqueness theorem for solutions diffeomorphic to a MGHD. These are called <em>globally hyperbolic spacetimes</em>.</p> <p>The expectation that the space of all solutions to Einstein’s equations contained exclusively globally hyperbolic spacetimes was, ironically, short-lived. By 1970, the Penrose-Hawking singularity theorems were fully developed. In the presence of spacetime singularities, inextensible differentiable timelike curves acquire finite proper time (they end). Thus, singularities represent boundaries for the MGHD. Additionally, they can spoil the global well-posedness in a number of other way, <em>e.g.</em>, uniqueness can be broken by caustics (the focusing of geodesics into a single point), see Figure 4.</p> <p>Penrose also very clearly defined the concept of Cauchy horizons (CHs). These are boundaries for the MGHD beyond which there are inextensible differentiable timelike curves that never punctured a Cauchy surface in the MGHD. In other words, a fragment of the movie that couldn’t be predicted from the initial snapshot.</p> <p>CHs are inevitable when closed timelike curves (CTCs) are present, <em>e.g.</em>, inside rotating black holes. CTC is just a fancy name for time travel. It breaks uniqueness by puncturing the would-be Cauchy surface many times over, see figure 5.</p> <p>Clearly, all these results indicated the very real (and embarrassing) possibility that GR indeed is not a globally well-posed theory, <em>i.e.</em>, it is not deterministic.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/svg/singularity.webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/svg/singularity.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Figure 4: A spacetime caustic. </div> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/svg/cauchyhorizon.webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/svg/cauchyhorizon.webp" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <div class="caption"> Figure 5: A Cauchy horizon harboring CTCs. </div> </div> </div> <h2 id="cosmic-censorship-conjectures">Cosmic Censorship Conjectures</h2> <p>The apparent ill-posedness of GR immediately bothered Penrose himself, making him conjecture that every singularity must be “hidden” inside an event horizon, known as the Weak Cosmic Censorship Conjecture (WCCC), and that Cauchy horizons are mathematical artifacts, unstable under metric perturbations. Thus, they could never survive gravitational collapse and form in Nature. This is known as the Strong Cosmic Censorship Conjecture (SCCC). If true, these conjectures would restore the deterministic nature of Einstein’s equations, even if only for infinitely far away (asymptotic) observers.</p> <p>Since the 1970s, there was a strong expectation in the scientific community that Penrose’s CCCs would eventually be proven true. Indeed, since then, we struggled to find any natural process able to generate stable naked singularities (singularities not “dressed” by an event horizon). If they do exist, they are quite rare. In addition, there is mounting evidence that Cauchy horizons are inherently unstable if matter fields respect the Weak Energy Conditions (WECs).</p> <p>So, how come, we are in the year 2025, and there is still no consensus in the scientific community about the real predictive power of GR? Well, the answer is, at least, 3-fold.</p> <p>Firstly, we know since the 1990s that WCCC is mathematically false. Physicists <a href="https://inspirehep.net/literature/34598">P. S. Joshi, I. H. Dwivedi</a>, <a href="https://inspirehep.net/literature/1235882">D. Christodoulou</a>, and others, have proven that naked singularities can form in specific cases through the collapse of matter. These results led famous physicist Stephen Hawking to <a href="https://www.preskill.caltech.edu/old_naked_bet.html">concede his original bet</a> against naked singularities. Indeed, GR appears to have no internal mechanism to prevent their formation.</p> <p>The only caveat is that these examples heavily rely on a specific set of Cauchy data (<em>e.g.</em>, with perfect spherical symmetry). Nonetheless, it might be only a matter of time until we figure out processes capable of generating them under very few assumptions, making naked singularities generic enough to occur in Nature.</p> <p>Secondly, SCCC may not hold true when quantum effects are taken into account. Quantum fields do not always adhere to WECs, and quantum gravity effects may further complicate this discussion. Either of these factors could potentially stabilize the Cauchy horizon, making it long-lived.</p> <p>Thirdly, and finally, SCCC has been proven mathematically false twice now, regardless of quantum effects. In 2003, M. Dafermos developed a <a href="https://inspirehep.net/literature/622602">proof of existence of the region across the CH inside charged (Reissner-Nordström) black holes</a>. And, in 2017, Dafermos and J. Luk, managed to develop a <a href="https://inspirehep.net/literature/1628644">similar proof for the CH inside rotating (Kerr) black holes</a>.</p> <p>The caveat is that these proofs hold only in the category of continuous spacetimes. The inherent instability of CHs when WECs are satisfied does not mean its interior region collapses out of existence into a singularity, as previously thought. Instead, in a much less dramatic manner, its smoothness ($C^\infty$ differentiability) collapses into just continuity ($C^0$). Black holes’ CHs, its interior region, and the metric field there survive the gravitational collapse but as continuous non-differentiable structures. Fair enough, if the metric is only $C^0$, then Einstein’s equations are not even valid there. And, once again, we are unable to draw further conclusions about their well-posedness.</p> <h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2> <p>GR’s situation looks grim at the moment. So much so, we are left to discuss sociological aspects of Physics.</p> <p>Most physicists today have adopted the optimistic view that “GR is such a good theory that it predicts its own demise”. And, that its ultraviolet completion, whatever it is, will clarify the nature of singularities, Cauchy horizons, <em>etc</em>., ultimately reestablishing the global well-posedness of the spacetime evolution.</p> <p>On the other hand, there is also the pessimistic (or realistic, depending on where you sit) branch. This branch takes these results at face value, and points out less singular alternatives to GR as paths forward. Additionally, it emphasizes that quantum gravity, something which we don’t agree on what it is even after +100 years of research, has no obligation to solve these issues. If it will, it’s anyone’s guess right now.</p> <p>Personally, I sit fuzzily in the middle. I acknowledge the optimistic point of view, which might very well be the path forward. However, I also cannot help but sense a bit of biased effort to save GR. To spin the narrative, and turn a bug into a feature via marketing tactics. I do not particularly subscript to this aspect of the optimistic branch.</p> <p>The pessimistic branch generally have good points. Alternatives to GR, sometimes for historical rather than scientific reasons, have been side lined. It immediately comes to my mind the Einstein-Cartan theory of gravity, which is capable of producing regular black holes and cosmological solutions, while fully agreeing with GR otherwise. However, I am also not convinced these alternatives are globally well-posed Cauchy problems. They tend to be less singular, yes, but singularities can still occur and global ill-posedness follows.</p> <p>Ironically, it seems that the resolution of all these problems might lie in our future Cauchy development.</p>]]></content><author><name>Guilherme Sadovski</name></author><category term="physics"/><category term="gr-qc"/><category term="math-phys"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An account of the Cauchy problem for Einstein's equations.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Symmetries and charges</title><link href="https://gsadovski.github.io/blog/2025/noether/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Symmetries and charges"/><published>2025-01-09T15:48:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-09T15:48:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gsadovski.github.io/blog/2025/noether</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gsadovski.github.io/blog/2025/noether/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>Amalie Emmy Noether is widely recognized as the most influential woman in the history of mathematics. Among her brilliant work, two theorems formulated in 1915 are known by every theoretical physicist. Noether’s theorems have impacted every branch of physics that involves the continuous evolution of a dynamical system.</p> <p>In mathematics, they are an important result in functional analysis and play a foundational role in algebraic topology, particularly the idea that algebraic structures can capture invariant properties of a space.</p> <p>The theorems establish a rigorous connection between the continuous symmetries of a dynamical system and its conservation laws. In classical and quantum field theory, they clarify how the presence of symmetries can constrain the dynamics, define charges, and even determine the physical states of a model.</p> <p>The theorems work in both directions. The presence of constrained dynamics and conserved charges also implies the existence of underlying symmetries. This is an extremely powerful result that shaped most of the 20th century physics.</p> <h2 id="prelude-in-classical-field-theory">Prelude in classical field theory</h2> <p>To begin, let’s consider $X$ a $n$-dimensional spacetime, and $\phi \left(x\right) \; ; \; x \in X$ a tensorial field over it with dynamics defined by the action functional</p> \[S \left[ \phi \right] \equiv \int_{X} \mathcal{L} \left( \phi, d \phi \right) \;,\] <p>where $d$ is the exterior derivative, and $\mathcal{L} \left( \phi, d \phi \right)$ is the $n$-form Lagrangian.</p> <p>Under an infinitesimal field variation, $\phi \mapsto \phi’ = \phi + \delta \phi$, which vanishes at the boundary $\partial X$ of $X$, the action functional will vary accordingly,</p> \[\delta S \left[\phi\right] = \int_{X} {\delta}^{(1)}_{\phi} \mathcal{L} \delta\phi \;,\] <p>where $ {\delta}^{(1)}_{\phi} \equiv \frac{\partial }{\partial \phi} - d \left[ \frac{\partial }{\partial \left(d \phi\right)}\right] $ is the Euler-Lagrange operator.</p> <p>Hamilton’s principle ($\delta S = 0$) then implies the Euler-Lagrange field equations</p> \[\delta^{(1)}_{\phi} \mathcal{L} = 0 \;,\] <p>which govern the classical dynamics of this field theory. In particular, its solutions are the extrema of $S$, and comprise the so-called “on-shell” configurations of $\phi$.</p> <h2 id="what-are-symmetries">What are symmetries?</h2> <p>First, consider a $\alpha$-parameter family of infinitesimal variations, $ \phi \mapsto \phi’ = \phi + \delta_{\xi ^{a}}\phi $ with $a \in \left\{1, \cdots, \alpha\right\} $, that do not necessarily vanish at $\partial X$. This family of field transformations is said to be continuous, $C^k$-differentiable, smooth, <em>etc.</em>, if the fields $\xi^{a} = \xi^a (x)$ are. For instance, if $\xi^a (x)$ are constants, the transformations are said to be global, otherwise they are local.</p> <p>We assume that $\delta_{\xi^{a}}\phi$ satisfy the axioms of an algebra. This algebra is finite-dimensional if the transformations are global, or infinite-dimensional if they are local. Very important examples in high-energy physics are the BRST and the Lie algebras. One should point out that, among these, only finite-dimensional Lie algebras are necessarily associated with the local properties of Lie groups. Symmetries are more widely associated with algebras, not groups.</p> <p>Second, $\xi^a$ are the elements of a quasi-symmetry algebra (of a classical field theory) if</p> \[\delta_{\xi^{a}} S = \int_{\partial X} K_{\xi^{a}} \;,\] <p>where $K_{\xi^{a}}$ is an $(n-1)$-form depending arbitrarily on $\phi$ and $d \phi$.</p> <p>Clearly, quasi-symmetries are on-shell exact-symmetries of a field theory since boundary terms do not contribute to the Euler-Lagrange field equations.</p> <h2 id="noethers-1st-theorem">Noether’s 1st theorem</h2> <p>The quasi-symmetry conditions above, when developed for the case of global transformations, lead to the so-called Noether identities,</p> \[\delta_{\phi}^{(1)} \mathcal{L} \delta_{\xi^{a}} \phi + d J_{\xi^{a}} = 0 \;, \tag{1}\label{eq:noetheridentities}\] <p>where</p> \[J_{\xi^{a}} \equiv \left[\frac{\partial \mathcal{L}}{\partial \left(d \phi\right)}\right] \delta_{\xi^{a}} \phi - K_{\xi^{a}}\] <p>are the so-called Noether currents. These identities exemplify how the presence of (quasi-)symmetry generators, $\delta_{\xi^{a}} \phi$, constrain the Euler-Lagrange term, $\delta_{\phi}^{(1)}\mathcal{L}$.</p> <p>Noether’s 1st theorem is a particular case of the Noether identities, restricted to on-shell field configurations. Explicitly, \eqref{eq:noetheridentities} reduces on-shell to a continuity equation, $d J_{\xi^{a}} = 0$. In other words, the presence of $\alpha$ global quasi-symmetry generators implies $\alpha$ on-shell conserved Noether currents, and <em>vice versa</em>. This is rigorously how symmetry algebra elements are connected to dynamical invariants.</p> <p>Finally, for each $J_{\xi^{a}}$ we have a so-called conserved Noether charge,</p> \[Q_{\xi^{a}} \equiv \int_{Y} J_{\xi^{a}} \;,\] <p>inside a spacelike $(n-1)$-submanifold $Y$ in $X$.</p> <h2 id="the-brst-symmetry-and-charge">The BRST symmetry and charge</h2> <p>As mentioned, the BRST symmetry algebra is an important example present in gauge theories of high-energy particle physics. Let’s consider the example of the Yang-Mills (YM) theories, which describe the ultraviolet dynamics of the strong and electronweak interactions. Classically, the YM dynamics is given by</p> \[S_{YM}[A] \equiv - \int_{X} \tr \left( F \star F \right) \;,\] <p>where $- \tr$ represents the Killing form on the Lie algebra $\mathfrak{g}$, $F=dA+A^2$ represents the $\mathfrak{g}$-valued 2-form curvature (field strength) of the $\mathfrak{g}$-valued 1-form connection $A$ (gauge field); and, $\star$ is the Hodge operator on $X$.</p> <p>The BRST algebra is a global exact-symmetry of YM action. Explicitly, $\delta_{BRST} S_{YM} = 0$ where $\delta_{BRST} A = -Dc$ and $\delta_{BRST} c = -c^2$; $D = d + \left[A, \phantom{A}\right] $ is the exterior covariant derivative in the adjoint representation; and $c$ is the $\mathfrak{g}$-valued 0-form Faddeev-Popov ghost field — introduced to make ${\delta_{BRST}}^2 = 0$.</p> <p>According to Noether’s 1st theorem, the BRST symmetry above then implies that the YM dynamics is off-shell constrained by \eqref{eq:noetheridentities}, and that there will be an on-shell conserved Noether current and charge, namely,</p> \[\begin{aligned} J_{BRST} &amp;= \tr \left( \star FDc \right) \;, \\ Q_{BRST} &amp;= \int_{Y} \tr \left( \star FDc\right) \;. \end{aligned}\] <p>In the absence of a gauge anomaly, the BRST symmetry survives the quantization process<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. Noether identities resurrect as the so-called Slavnov-Taylor identities, which constrain the quantum correlation functions and guarantee that quantum YM theory is unitary and renormalizable to all orders in perturbation theory. Additionally, the Noether charge $Q_{BRST}$ becomes a nilpotent operator ${\hat{Q}_{BRST}}^2 = 0$, acting on the YM Fock space, $\mathcal{F}$. If not enough, its cohomology</p> \[H \left(\hat{Q}_{BRST}\right) \equiv \left\{ \hat{Q}_{BRST} \lvert \text{phys} \rangle = 0 \; ; \; \lvert \text{phys} \rangle \neq \hat{Q}_{BRST}\lvert \text{something} \rangle \right\}\] <p>isomorphically defines the subspace $ \mathcal{F}_{\text{phys}} \subset \mathcal{F} $ of physical states of the YM field.</p> <h2 id="u1-symmetry-and-conservation-of-electric-charge">u(1) symmetry and conservation of electric charge</h2> <p>Noether’s 1st theorem allows us to associate the existence of a global $\mathfrak{u}(1)$ symmetry algebra with the conservation of electric charge in Dirac’s theory. For the non-physicists, this theory describes spin-half fermions like electrons, quarks, muons, <em>etc</em>.</p> <p>The dynamics of Dirac’s theory is defined by</p> \[S_{\text{Dirac}} \left[\psi, \bar{\psi} \right] \equiv \int_{X} \left[ \bar{\psi} \left( i \slashed{\nabla} - m \right) \psi \right] \eta \;.\] <p>where $\hbar=1$ (natural units); $\psi$ is the 0-form Dirac spinor, and $\bar{\psi} \equiv {\psi}^{\dagger} \gamma^{0}$ its adjoint; $\slashed{\nabla} \equiv \gamma \rfloor \nabla$ uses the Feynman slashed notation, $\gamma \equiv \gamma^{\mu} \partial_{\mu}$ is the 1-vector of gamma matrices, and $\rfloor$ is the interior product; $\nabla = d + \Gamma$ is the exterior covariant derivative of the Levi-Civita connection $\Gamma$ in the spinorial representation; $m$ is a mass parameter, and $\eta \equiv \star \mathbb{1}$ is the unitary $n$-form volume in $X$.</p> <p>The generator $\delta_{\xi} \psi = -i \xi \psi$ ($\delta_{\xi} \bar{\psi} = i \xi \bar{\psi}$), satisfies the $\mathfrak{u}(1)$ Lie algebra. According to Noether’s 1st theorem, the global exact-symmetry $\delta_{\xi} S_{\text{Dirac}} = 0$ then implies the existence of a conserved Noether current and charge. Respectively,</p> \[\begin{aligned} J_{\xi} &amp;= \xi \bar{\psi} \slashed{\eta} \psi \;, \\ Q_{\xi} &amp;= \xi \int_{Y} \bar{\psi} \slashed{\eta} \psi \;, \end{aligned}\] <p>where $\slashed{\eta } \equiv \gamma \rfloor \eta$. In particular, $Q_{\text{electric}} \equiv Q_{\xi}/\xi$ is the actual physical observable that we call the electric charge of $\psi$.</p> <h2 id="translations-and-conservation-of-energy-momentum">Translations and conservation of energy-momentum</h2> <p>Global translations are a 1-parameter family of automorphisms on $X$, generated by the presence of a globally well-defined, smooth, and constant, vector field $\xi = \xi^{\mu} \partial_{\mu}$. This field exists if, and only if, $X$ is globally flat ($\nabla = d$ everywhere).</p> <p>Translations non-trivially transform the spacetime itself, which is quite different from the BRST or the $\mathfrak{u}(1)$ transformations, which only act non-trivially on certain fields over the spacetime. In particular, every natural tensor field transforms under translations. This is a functorial property shared by all natural bundles over $X$.</p> <p>The algebra of translations has generator $\delta_{\xi}\phi = L_{\xi} \phi$, where $L_{\xi} \equiv \xi\rfloor d + d\xi\rfloor$ is the Lie derivative along $\xi$. It is easy to demonstrate that</p> \[\delta_{\xi} S \left[\phi\right] = \int_{X} d \left(\xi \rfloor \mathcal{L}\right)\] <p>for any $S \left[\phi\right]$, because $\left(n+1\right)$-forms always vanish. This goes to show that, as long as $\xi$ exists on $X$, then translations will be a quasi-symmetry of any (natural) tensorial field theories over it.</p> <p>Again, we evoke Noether’s 1st theorem to imply a conserved current and charge,</p> \[J_{\xi} = \left[ \frac{\partial \mathcal{L}}{\partial \left(d \phi\right)} \right] L_{\xi} \phi - \xi \rfloor \mathcal{L} \;, \tag{2}\label{eq:energy-momentum}\] \[Q_{\xi} = \int_{Y} \left\{ \left[ \frac{\partial \mathcal{L}}{\partial \left(d \phi\right)} \right] L_{\xi} \phi - \xi \rfloor \mathcal{L} \right\} \;. \tag{3}\label{eq:total-energy}\] <p>The Noether current \eqref{eq:energy-momentum} is the $(n-1)$-form known as the energy-momentum density of $\phi$. Meanwhile, the corresponding Noether charge \eqref{eq:total-energy} is our traditional concept of the total energy of $\phi$ inside the $(n-1)$-volume $Y$.</p> <p>It is time now, to put a stop to the myth that energy is always conserved. It should be clear that in the presence of a gravitational field, $X$ is not flat and $\xi$ is not globally well-defined. Since there is no global algebra of translations, there is also no global (quasi-)symmetry under translations. Noether’s 1st theorem is not applicable, and no translational Noether charge (conserved energy) is well-defined. In fact, this is precisely why gravitational redshift occurs. Simply, the energy of the electromagnetic field is not generally conserved on a curved background.</p> <p>The non-conservation of energy is not a bad thing. In fact, the afterglow of the Big Bang, known as the cosmic microwave background (CMB), is now completely invisible and has an average temperature of only 2.7 Kelvins above the absolute zero (approx. –270.4°C) due to it. If energy were conserved, no stars, planets, or life would be possible. It would be too hot for even the atomic nuclei or hadrons (protons, neutrons, <em>etc.</em>) to exist.</p> <h2 id="noethers-2nd-theorem">Noether’s 2nd theorem</h2> <p>Noether’s 2nd theorem sprouts out of Noether identities, but for the case of a local (gauge) quasi-symmetry algebra,</p> \[\int_{X} \left[ \delta_{\phi}^{(1)} \mathcal{L} \delta_{\xi^{a}(x)} \phi + d J_{\xi^{a}(x)}\right] = 0 \;. \tag{4}\label{eq:local-noetheridentities}\] <p>Notice that the integral was kept because its result depends on the particular choice of $\xi^a(x)$, and its asymptotic behavior.</p> <p>Equation \eqref{eq:local-noetheridentities} is a common source of confusion, often stemming from a misunderstanding of the distinction between “proper” <em>versus</em> “improper” gauge transformations. Proper gauge transformations are characterized by $\xi^{a}(x)$ having compact support in $X$. In particular, $\xi^{a}\mid_{\partial X} = 0$. On the other hand, improper gauge transformations lack compact support in $X$, and notably, $\xi^{a}\mid_{\partial X} \neq 0$. This distinction is important because it makes \eqref{eq:local-noetheridentities} imply very different things.</p> <p>For the case of proper gauge transformations, \eqref{eq:local-noetheridentities} reduce to the constraints $\delta_{\phi}^{(1)}\mathcal{L}\delta_{\xi^{a}(x)}\phi = 0$, and imply that all Noether charges vanish, $Q_{\xi^{a}(x)} = 0$. This is what’s behind the myth “gauge symmetries only generate trivial Noether charges”. On the other hand, the improper case behaves pretty much like global symmetries. In fact, both satisfy $\xi^{a}\mid_{\partial X} \neq 0$. Then, Noether’s 2nd theorem implies the existence of non-trivial Noether charges on $\partial X$. These are the so-called <em>asymptotic charges</em>, extremely relevant today in the study of (hairy) black holes, holographic models, and low-dimensional quantum gravity.</p> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1"> <p>The BRST quantization process involves modifying the YM action by adding gauge-fixing terms, and possibly non-linearity terms, which inevitably alter the explicit form of $J_{BRST}$ and $Q_{BRST}$. Therefore, the form given here is not really the one used in a perturbative quantum field theory context, as it is plagued with gauge redundancies. Still, it is mathematically and physically correct from a classical standpoint. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name>Guilherme Sadovski</name></author><category term="physics"/><category term="math"/><category term="math-phys"/><category term="classft"/><category term="hep-th"/><category term="gr-qc"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The work of the most influencial woman in the history of mathematics]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can black holes work as windmills?</title><link href="https://gsadovski.github.io/blog/2024/penrose-process/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can black holes work as windmills?"/><published>2024-12-13T14:17:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-12-13T14:17:00+00:00</updated><id>https://gsadovski.github.io/blog/2024/penrose-process</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://gsadovski.github.io/blog/2024/penrose-process/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2> <p>In General Relativity, the Kerr family is a class of exact vacuum solutions to Einstein’s equations, $R_{\mu \nu} = 0$, describing the spacetime geometry around a stationary, uncharged, rotating point-like mass distribution.</p> <p>The overall structure of a Kerr metric is quite complex, with multiple horizons, extended singularities, closed timelike curves (CTCs), ergosurfaces, <em>etc</em>. These features, resulting from the absence of temporal and spherical symmetry, also provide a more realistic description of astrophysical objects. After all, most things you see in a telescope are spinning. In particular, the Kerr black hole is widely recognized as the last stage in the evolution of sufficiently massive stars.</p> <p>In 1969, physicist Roger Penrose proposed a theoretical mechanism for extracting energy from a Kerr black hole. This process can only take place in-between the black hole’s event horizon and exterior ergosurface, known as the ergoregion. From the perspective of an asymptotic observer (infinitely far away), the ergoregion forbids static frames of reference due to an extreme Lense-Thirring effect. Those who resist being “dragged” may acquire negative energies. It is the absorption of negative energy particles that enables the Kerr black hole to be spun down, and an effective energy extraction to take place.</p> <h2 id="the-kerr-metric">The Kerr metric</h2> <p>The Kerr family is a class of axially symmetric stationary exact vacuum solutions to Einstein’s equations. That’s a mouthful which, for asymptotic observers utilizing traditional spherical coordinates $(t,r,\theta,\phi)$, and natural units ($c=G=1$), means</p> \[g(t,r,\theta,\phi) = g_{ tt } dt^2 + g_{ t \phi } dt d \phi + g_{ \phi t } d \phi dt + g_{ rr } dr^2 + g_{ \theta \theta } d\theta^2 + g_{ \phi \phi } d \phi^2 \;,\] <p>where</p> \[g_{tt} = - \left(1 - \frac{ r_{S} r }{ \rho^2 } \right) \;,\] \[g_{t\phi} = g_{\phi t} = \frac{ - r_{S}ra\sin^2\theta }{ \rho^2 }\;,\] \[g_{rr} = \frac{ \rho^2 }{ \Delta }\;,\] \[g_{\theta\theta} = \rho^2\;,\] \[g_{\phi\phi} = \left[(r^2 + a^2)^2 - \Delta a^2 \sin^2\theta\right]\frac{ \sin^2\theta }{ \rho^2 } \;.\] <p>The notation used is $r_{S} \equiv 2M $, $ \rho^2 \equiv r^2 + a^2\cos^2\theta $, $ \Delta \equiv r^2 - r_S r + {a}^2$, and $ a \equiv J/M $.</p> <p>The Kerr family is parametrized by 2 quantities, $ M $ and $ J $, usually interpreted as the mass and angular momentum of the central spinning body, respectively. If the Kerr family comprises valid interior solutions, then we really want the bound $ J \leq M $ to be respected. The region $J&gt;M$ of the parameter space is populated not with black holes, but with naked singularities: quite obscene objects which exposes to the world physical pathologies usually hidden inside an event horizon.</p> <p>We should point out that off-diagonal terms, $g_{t \phi} = g_{\phi t}$, make evident the presence of the Lense-Thirring effect due to the black hole’s rotation in the azimuthal direction, $ \hat{\phi} \equiv \partial_{\phi} / \sqrt{g_{\phi \phi}} $. Additionally, one can visually inspect that all metric components above are explicitly independent of $t$ and $\phi$. This implies that $\partial_{t}$ and $\partial_{\phi}$ are Killing vectors of these solutions — a direct consequence of their stationary and axially symmetric nature.</p> <p>Last but not least:</p> <ul> <li>The limit $a \rightarrow 0$, $M$ fixed, results in the Schwarzschild geometry;</li> <li>The limit $a$ fixed, $M\rightarrow 0$, results in Minkowski;</li> <li>The Kerr family is asymptotically flat, which results in asymptotic observers being inertial;</li> <li>Although stationary, the Kerr family is not static, <em>e.g.</em>, time reflections flip the rotation’s direction.</li> </ul> <h2 id="horizons-and-ergosurfaces">Horizons and ergosurfaces</h2> <p>Firstly, notice how the metric component $g_{rr}$ becomes singular at $\Delta=0$. This indicates the presence of horizons at $(t,r_{H}^{\pm},\theta,\phi)$, where</p> \[r_{H}^{\pm} \equiv \frac{ \left(r_{S} \pm \sqrt{r_{S}^2 - 4a^2}\right) }{ 2 } \;.\] <p>The outer horizon, $r_{H}^{+}$, is the actual event horizon of the Kerr black hole. The inner one, $r_{H}^{-}$, is a Cauchy horizon: a boundary beyond which the determinism of Einstein’s equations breaks down (see <em><a href="/blog/2025/cauchy-problem">How predictive is General Relativity?</a></em>).</p> <p>Secondly, most of the metric components are singular at $\rho^2=0$. This is the ring-shaped singularity at $(t,0,\pi/2,\phi)$. In its vicinity CTCs exist, which leads to violations of causality conditions.</p> <p>Thirdly, and finally, the metric component $g_{tt}$ vanishes at $\rho^{2}=r_{S}r$. This defines the hypersurfaces $(t,r_{E}^{\pm},\theta,\phi)$, known as static limit and/or infinite redshift surfaces (<em>a.k.a.</em>, ergosurfaces), where</p> \[r_{E}^{\pm} \equiv \frac{ \left(r_{S} \pm \sqrt{r_{S}^2 - 4a^2\cos^2\theta}\right) }{ 2 } \;.\] <p>Their own definition makes them also a Killing horizon generated by $\partial_{t}$. This is just a fancy way to say that the norm of $\partial_{t}$ vanishes (changes sign) at $r^{\pm}_{E}$. But keep this in mind as Killing horizons explain energies changing signs in the perspective of asymptotic observers!</p> <p>It should be clear that $r_{E}^{+} \geq r_{H}^{+} &gt; r_{H}^{-} \geq r_{E}^{-}$, with the equalities only holding at the poles $(t,r,0,\phi)$ and $(t,r,\pi,\phi)$, see Figure 1. In particular, the region $r \leq r_{H}^{-}$ is widely contested in the scientific community due to the physical pathologies already mentioned (lack of determinism, causality, etc.). Again, check <em><a href="/blog/2025/cauchy-problem">How predictive is General Relativity?</a></em> for a more detailed account. Here, we’re going to discuss only the region $r \geq r_{H}^{+}$.</p> <div align="center"> <script type="text/tikz">
\begin{tikzpicture}
    % Outer ergosurface
    \fill[gray!70] (0,0) ellipse (4 and 2);
    \node[gray] at (4.3,0) {$r_{E}^+$};
    % Outer event horizon
    \fill[black] (0,0) ellipse (2.7 and 2);
    \node at (3,0) {$r_{H}^+$};
    % Inner event Horizon
    \draw[dashed, gray] (0,0) ellipse ( 2 and 1.2) ;
    \node[gray!70] at (2.3,0) {$r_{H}^-$};
    % Inner ergosurface
    \draw[dashed, gray] (0,0) ellipse ( 1.3 and 1.2) ;
    \node[gray!70] at (1.6,0) {$r_{E}^-$};
    % Ring Singularity
    \draw[thick, red] (0,0) ellipse ( 1.3 and 0.3) ;
    % Parameters
    \node[gray!70] at (0,.7) {$M$, $J$};
\end{tikzpicture}
</script> <div class="caption"> Figure 1: Schematics of the Kerr black hole </div> </div> <h2 id="the-lense-thirring-effect">The Lense-Thirring effect</h2> <p>Let’s consider a differentiable curve $\gamma(\tau)$ near a Kerr black hole. The affine parameter $\tau$ represents its proper time, and $\dot{\gamma}(\tau) \equiv d\gamma/d\tau$ its 4-velocity. For our convenience, let’s also assume that, for an asymptotic observer, $\gamma(\tau)$ is static in the radial and zenithal directions, $\dot{\gamma}^{r}=\dot{\gamma}^{\theta}=0$.</p> <p>The inequality $g\left(\dot{\gamma},\dot{\gamma}\right) &lt; 0$ is sufficient for $\gamma\left(\tau\right)$ to be timelike — this is the kind of curve massive particles follow. But, it also implies the inequalities $\Omega^{-}&lt;\Omega&lt;\Omega^{+}$, where $\Omega \equiv {\dot{\gamma}}^{\phi}/{\dot{\gamma}}^{t}$ is the azimuthal velocity, and</p> \[\Omega^{\pm} \equiv \omega \pm \sqrt{\omega^2-4 \frac{g_{tt}}{g_{\phi\phi}}} \; ; \; \omega \equiv - \frac{g_{t\phi}}{g_{\phi\phi}} \;.\] <p>In other words, for an asymptotic observer, the azimuthal velocities of massive particles are always limited to the open interval $(\Omega^{-},\Omega^{+})$. Otherwise, we would have supraluminal speeds, causality violation, etc. Not physically desirable things.</p> <p>In the exterior region of a Kerr black hole, $r &gt; r_{E}^{+}$, we have $g_{tt} &lt; 0$, $\Omega^{-} &lt; 0$, and $\Omega^{+} &gt; 0$. Massive particles are free to follow $\gamma(\tau)$ at subluminal speeds in the direction of the black hole’s rotation ($\Omega &gt; 0$), against it ($\Omega &lt; 0$), or even remain spatially static ($\Omega = 0$). This is all normal behavior we expect.</p> <p>Things start to change on the ergosurface though. At $r = r_{E}^{+}$, $g_{tt} = 0$ because we are on the Killing horizon (!) of $\partial_{t}$. As a result, $\Omega^{-} = 0$ and $\Omega^{+} = 2\omega$. Now, every massive particle that follows $\gamma(\tau)$ is forced to do it in the direction of the black hole’s rotation, and spatial static ($\Omega = 0$) is a luxury that only massless particles can enjoy. In other words, light, which follow null trajectories, $g\left(\dot{\gamma},\dot{\gamma}\right) = 0$, can be at a full stop on the ergosurface.</p> <p>Finally, in the ergoregion $r_{E}^{+} &lt; r &lt; r_{H}^{+}$, we have $g_{tt} &gt; 0$, and $\Omega^{\pm} &gt; 0$. Spatial static is now forbidden to everyone. With no exceptions, every non-spacelike trajectory is forcefully oriented by the black hole’s rotation. Here, asymptotic frames cannot avoid the black hole’s drag just like they cannot avoid the future. This is purely due to the warping of space and time, and represent perhaps the most extreme version of the often tiny Lense-Thirring effect.</p> <p>Now, we can explicitly calculate $\omega$ for the Kerr family. It is given by</p> \[\omega = \frac{r_{S}ra}{(r^2 + a^2)^2 - \Delta a^2\sin^2\theta } \;.\] <p>On the event horizon, $\omega = \omega_{H}$, where $\omega_{H} \equiv a / r_{S}r_{H}^{+}$. Additionally, $\Omega^{\pm}=\omega_{H}$. In other words, everyone is forced to follow the black hole’s rotation at a precisely determined azimuthal speed. Since the properties of particles clearly don’t matter here, $\omega_{H}$ can be seen as intrinsic to the black hole. It is the rotational speed of its event horizon.</p> <h2 id="negative-energies-and-momenta">Negative energies and momenta</h2> <p>We have just discussed how an extreme Lense-Thirring effect occurs inside the ergosurface of a Kerr black hole. When crossing this spacetime boundary, the azimuthal component of your 4-velocity, $\dot{\gamma}^{\phi}$, is required to change by the ratio $\Omega$, in order to offset the sign change that had just occurred in $\dot{\gamma}^{t}$. The latter is due to the ergosurface coinciding with the Killing horizon (!) of $\partial_{t}$, but the former is to ensure that every observer agrees on the timelike nature of $\gamma$. In other words, that $g(\dot{\gamma},\dot{\gamma}) &lt; 0$ remains a frame-invariant inequality.</p> <p>A similar analysis can be done for the 4-momentum $p = m \dot{\gamma}$ of a particle with mass $m$ following $\gamma$. Upon entering the ergoregion, the momentum component $p_{t} \equiv g\left(\partial_{t},p\right)$ changes sign, and $p_{\phi}$ must adjust accordingly to maintain the inequality $g \left(p,p\right) &lt; 0$ frame-invariant. The particularly interesting point here is that $p_{t} = - E$ and $p_{\phi} = L$, where $E$ is the energy and $L$ the azimuthal angular momentum of this particle. Thus, asymptotic observers can witness a particle’s energy change sign when it crosses the Kerr ergosurface.</p> <p>The negative energy condition, $E &lt; 0$, can be expressed as $\Omega &lt; - g_{tt}/g_{t \phi}$. Outside the ergoregion ($r &gt; r_{E}^{+}$), this condition can only be satisfied by spacelike curves, as it implies supraluminal speeds. The same is true at the ergosurface ($r = r_{E}^{+}$), where $g_{tt} = 0$. However, within the ergoregion ($r_{E}^{+} &lt; r &lt; r_{H}^{+}$), we find that $g_{tt} &gt; 0$, and the negative energy condition, clearly intersects with the non-spacelike conditions ($\Omega^{-} \leq \Omega \leq \Omega^{+}$). “Sufficiently slow” particles (${\Omega}^{-} \leq \Omega &lt; - g_{tt}/g_{t \phi}$) — those who resist the Lense-Thirring effect just enough — have negative energies from the perspective of an asymptotic observer. “Sufficiently fast” ones ($- g_{tt}/g_{t \phi} &lt; \Omega \leq \Omega^{+}$) have positive energies, and there are still those in a state of zero energy ($\Omega = - g_{tt} / g_{t \phi}$). Yes, black hole physics can be quite weird!</p> <p>To conclude this section, consider the Killing vector $k = \partial_{t} + \omega_{H} \partial_{\phi}$. It generates the Killing horizon coinciding with the event horizon of the Kerr black hole. The timelike condition $g \left(k, p\right) &lt; 0$ leads us to the inequality $E &gt; \omega_{H} L$. Thus, negative energy particles also have negative angular momenta — even though their orbital speeds are positive. As we will see next, it is the existence of these particles that enables the energy extraction to take place.</p> <h2 id="the-penrose-process">The Penrose process</h2> <p>The Penrose process presents a theoretical mechanism to extract usable energy from a rotating Kerr black hole. It is based on the existence of an ergoregion, which allows for timelike trajectories with negative energies and orbital momenta.</p> <p>Consider an electron coming from the asymptotic infinity, with initial positive energy $E_{0}$, following the timelike trajectory $\gamma_{1}$, which at some point enters the ergoregion of the Kerr black hole, check Figure 2. Also consider that, due to the gravitational acceleration, a photon will be emitted at some point. We assume that the electron will emit this photon within the ergoregion, and at such a precise angle that this photon will be one of those “slow enough” particles carrying negative energy $\varepsilon &lt; 0$. Let it follow the null trajectory $\gamma_{2}$ that ultimately falls into the event horizon. At the emission event, momentum conservation dictates that the trajectory of the electron needs to change, let it be the timelike $\gamma_{3}$ with positive energy $E_{f}$, that ultimately escapes to the asymptotic infinity.</p> <div align="center"> <script type="text/tikz">
\begin{tikzpicture}
    % Outer ergosurface
    \fill[gray!70] (0,0) ellipse (4 and 2);
    \node[gray] at (4.3,0) {$r_{E}^+$};
    % Outer event horizon
    \fill[black] (0,0) ellipse (2.7 and 2);
    \node at (3,0) {$r_{H}^+$};
    % Parameters
    \node[gray] at (0,.7) {$M$, $J$};
    % Inner event Horizon
    \draw[dashed, gray] (0,0) ellipse ( 2 and 1.2) ;
    \node[gray!70] at (2.3,0) {$r_{H}^-$};
    % Inner ergosurface
    \draw[dashed, gray] (0,0) ellipse ( 1.3 and 1.2) ;
    \node[gray!70] at (1.6,0) {$r_{E}^-$};
    % Ring Singularity
    \draw[thick, red] (0,0) ellipse ( 1.3 and 0.3) ;
    % Trajectories
    \draw[ dotted, thick, blue!50] (-5.5,-0.4) -- (-5,-0.5);
    \draw[ >-, thick, blue!50] (-5,-0.5) .. controls (-1.5,-1.2) .. (0.5,-1) node[midway,below] {$\gamma_1$};
    \draw[-, thick, blue!50] (0.5,-1) .. controls (1,-.5) .. (1,0) node[midway,right] {$\gamma_2$};
    \node[yellow!50] at (1.04,0) {$\times$};
    \draw[->, thick, blue!50] (0.5,-1) .. controls (1.5,-1) .. (3,-2) node[midway,below] {$\gamma_3$};
    \draw[ dotted, thick, blue!50] (3,-2) -- (3.5,-2.3);
\end{tikzpicture}
</script> <div class="caption"> Figure 2: Penrose process </div> </div> <p>In this highly theoretical scenario, energy conservation $E_{0} = E_{f} + \varepsilon$ of the electron-photon system dictates $\Delta E = - \varepsilon &gt; 0$, where $\Delta E \equiv E_{f} - E_{0}$. For an asymptotic observer witnessing the whole process, the electron escaped the neighborhood of the Kerr black hole with energy $E_{0} + \Delta E$. Saying it differently, the electron just extracted $\Delta E$ of energy from a Kerr black hole!</p> <p>In order for the Penrose process to be irreversible, the emitted photon really needs to fall into the event horizon. Additionally, since no lunch is free, this also means that there will be a subtraction $\delta M = \varepsilon$ and $\delta J = L$ (remember, both $\varepsilon$ and $L$ are negative), of the black hole mass and angular momentum in such a way that the inequality $\delta M &gt; \omega_{H} \delta J$ holds.</p> <p>As a final note, a series of Penrose energy extraction processes can bring the black hole to a thermodynamic equilibrium, defined by $\delta M = \omega_{H} \delta J$. Remarkably, this is recognizable as the 1st Law of Black Hole Thermodynamics, applicable to processes that maintain the area $A$ of the event horizon constant, $\delta A = 0$ (or, equivalently, the Bekenstein-Hawking (BH) entropy constant, $\delta S_{\text{BH}} = 0$).</p> <p>The thermodynamic equilibrium serves as a maximum limit for Penrose processes: attempting to extract more energy would violate the 2nd Law of Black Hole Thermodynamics, meaning that $A$ cannot shrink, $\delta A \geq 0$ (or, equivalently, $\delta S_{BH} \geq 0$). This limit is reached before $J=0$ is achieved, so Penrose processes cannot fully spin down the Kerr black hole. Putting it differently, Penrose processes do not provide a physical mechanism for the “spacetime decay” $\text{Kerr} \rightarrow \text{Schwarzschild}$.</p> <h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2> <p>The Penrose process was the first theoretical example demonstrating that energy extraction from a black hole could be possible. However, as we have just seen, it clearly requires very precise spacetime trajectories. Such a specific set of initial data make Penrose processes unlikely to happen in a natural astrophysical setting.</p> <p>Less fine-tuned mechanisms have been developed since, among which the Blandford-Znajek process is believed to be the engine powering the brightest objects in the entire Universe: Active Galactic Nuclei (AGNs) inside Quasars.</p> <p>In the end, rotating black holes appears to function as engines after all, similar to how windmills do.</p>]]></content><author><name>Guilherme Sadovski</name></author><category term="physics"/><category term="gr-qc"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Penrose process in Kerr black holes]]></summary></entry></feed>